we continue now with our overview of the
history of philosophy we turn our
attention today
to certainly one of the most prodigious
and formidable thinkers that the world
has ever known
and I'm thinking of course of Saint
Thomas Aquinas
Thomas was born in the 13th century in
the year 1224 presumably we're not
exactly sure of that year
but he died in the year 1274 before his
50th birthday so that he was 49 years
old at the time of his death and that in
itself is astonishing when you think of
the prodigious work that came from this
Titan a philosophical and Theological
thought
affectionately within the Roman Catholic
Church Saint Thomas is called the Dr
Angelicus or the Angelic Doctrine and no
single individual has done more to shape
the Theology of the Roman Catholic
Church than Thomas
although many Protestants also claim him
as a
as a one of the fathers of the faith
because so much of what he wrote and did
happened before the disputes that arose
in the 16th century
but the normal uh
Evangelical rap against Saint Thomas
Aquinas
is that he was guilty of separating
nature and Grace in fact
in the work of Francis Schaefer
when he gave his overview big picture
analysis of the breakdown of of thinking
in modern times he saw Aquinas as the
chief culprit for dividing the Spheres
of knowledge and making an unnatural
disjunction between nature and Grace by
separating them
and I was a personal friend of Francis
Schaefer and a great admirer and
respecter of him but on this point I
strongly disagreed with him
and I think to understand Thomas Aquinas
we have to understand
the issues he was facing in his day and
the problems he was seeking to solve and
one of the things that we're not all
that familiar with in the west is the
development of Eastern thought and
particularly Arabic thought we tend to
think of the Renaissance as being
strictly a a western phenomenon that
began in Florence and in the 13th
century with the rediscovery of the
ancient Greeks and so on but that was
already going on in Islamic philosophy
the great Islamic philosophers had
already rediscovered the Ancients and
at the time of Aquinas the great
thinkers of the Arab philosophers people
like avaros and avacynus had sought to
construct a synthesis between
Muslim theology
and Aristotelian philosophy and that's a
a study in and of itself but one of the
things that they came up with in their
synthesis was called the double truth
Theory
the double truth Theory this is a very
important idea in the history of
theoretical thought
the double truth Theory basically said
this
that something can be true
in philosophy
and false in religion at the same time
or it can be true by faith
but false in science at the same time
now let's translate that idea
to contemporary categories we see the
Raging controversy that goes on about
human Origins
are we as human beings the product of a
purposive Act of divine creation
or are we merely fortuitous Cosmic
accidents grown-up germs that have
spontaneously come out of a chance
Collision of atoms and so on
obviously
we cannot both be
purposefully created by a self-existent
Eternal God and at the same time be
Cosmic accidents those two concepts
cannot be reconciled but a double truth
thinker would say this well I'm a
religious person but I'm also a
scientist and so
on Monday Wednesdays and Fridays I will
believe in creation and on Tuesdays
Thursdays and Saturdays I believe in man
as a cosmic accident and
on Sunday I'll rest from the controversy
do you see what's going on here is a
separation or a disjunction between
faith and reason between philosophy and
religion between Theology and science
where the two don't meet or ever overlap
now it's precisely against that kind of
thinking that Saint Thomas Aquinas who
had been the illustrious student of
Albert the Great and who had been called
by his student
classmates while he was in school the
dumb Ox of Aquino to which Albert the
Great replied this dumb Ox is going to
astonish the world with his Brilliance
but in any case it was against this kind
of thinking
that Aquinas was responding because he
realized that if you had that kind of
disjunction between faith and reason and
antithesis between science and religion
uh you would end up as an intellectual
schizophrenic and it would make
truth impossible
to reconcile
and so what he did was he said
that
there are certain truths
that we learn from nature
and other truths that we learn from
Grace
and what he means by that is something
like this
if you study nature you can learn
something about the circulatory system
of the human body
but you can read the Bible all you want
and the Bible will not reveal to you the
intricacies of the circulatory system of
the human body or the molecular
structure of a leaf that you have to
apply natural science and and so on to
empirical investigation to discover that
sort of thing so you get certain truths
truths that don't contradict the
scriptures or contradict special
revelation
but you don't find that content in the
Bible
you find other truths according to
Aquinas that are revealed to us only in
the Bible that you can't discover with
the microscope or with a telescope
for example
the God's Plan of Salvation
you can't study that in a laboratory you
get that through the revelation of
scripture
so you have two sources
of Truth
Grace and nature now maybe the
distinction the words that he uses are a
little bit unfortunate and misleading
because one thing that Thomas did not
believe in was that nature functions or
exists
independent from God
but what he has in view here is more
like the distinction we make in theology
between
special Revelation and general
Revelation special Revelation is that
Revelation that comes to us in scripture
and general Revelation is that which is
comes through nature through the created
order the heavens declare the glory of
God the firmament shows its handiwork
and so on
but both of those are truths that come
from God
Paul for example in the first chapter of
Romans where he is engaged in the
writing of special Revelation says that
in addition to that Revelation that
comes in scripture there is the
Revelation that God gives of himself in
and through nature or the things that
are made so that the Bible itself says
there's another source of Revelation
namely nature that is also God's
revelation
now the point is this
Thomas Aquinas
distinguished between nature and Grace
he distinguished between faith and
reason
between philosophy and Science and so on
but as I try to teach my students in the
Seminary one of the most important
distinctions you will ever learn and
keep in mind that if it's the
prerogative of the woman to change her
mind it is the prerogative of the
Theologian to make fine distinctions
that's our stock and trade one of the
most important distinctions you will
ever learn is the distinction between a
distinction and a separation
if I distinguish your body from your
soul I bring no harm to you
if I separate your body from your soul
I've killed you so that there's a huge
difference between distinguishing and
separating
now Thomas certainly distinguished
between nature and Grace
but not for the purpose of separating
them
but for the purpose of showing their
ultimate unity
because even as Augustine had said
earlier that the Christian ought to
learn about as many things as he
possibly can
because he was convinced that all truth
is God's truth and all truth that is
truly true meets at the top so Aquinas
believe that what God reveals in nature
will never
contradict what he reveals in Scripture
so that there is a fundamental Harmony
between these two sources of knowledge
now so far so good with Aquinas and then
in addition to these two sources he then
added another category and the category
he called the articulus mixed us and
we'll put that in English the mixed
articles
and the mixed articles according to
Aquinas are those truths
that can be learned
either from scripture
or from nature
now here's where the controversy comes
in
Christians have not argued that the
Bible
teaches the existence of God
that's clear
and you can learn the premise that God
exists by reading the Bible
but the issue is can you learn of the
existence of God simply by studying
nature
that is is there such a thing
as natural
theology
natural theology has been a a bug bear
among 20th century theologians and
there's been great
antipathy expressed against Natural
theology
now
natural revelation
refers to God's self-disclosure in the
realm of nature
natural natural Revelation is something
God does he's the revealer
natural theology is something we do
namely the question is this
if nature reveals God
do we learn anything from that
revelation
if we learn anything from that
Revelation if we gain any knowledge of
God
from that natural Revelation than what
do we have we have natural
theology because all the word theology
means is the knowledge of God now you
may argue forever about the scope of
that knowledge the extent of that
knowledge the accuracy of that knowledge
and all the other debates that that
focus on this question but that there is
natural knowledge of God
I think couldn't be any more manifest
than what Paul teaches in the first
chapter of Romans and when Thomas
Aquinas was talking about his concept of
natural theology he did it not simply on
a speculative basis of of uh reasoning
but he did it exegetically he turned the
attention of his readers to Paul's
teaching in the first chapter of Romans
to justify this but then of course what
he's most known known for in the western
world is not his his exposition of the
Bible but for his rational arguments for
the existence of God
he's trying to say well if nature
reveals that God is how does that happen
how do we understand a knowledge of God
simply by looking at creation and he set
forth five proofs for the existence of
God wherein he was reasoning from the
created world back to the first cause or
the Creator now again many of his
critics say that to argue for God
cosmologically that is from the cosmos
back to the creator of the cosmos
is to get you no further than
Aristotle's first cause his uncaused
cause
I always say to those critics be careful
here
because that uh you know these people
who say well the god of the philosophers
is not the god of Christianity because
our God is so much more than a first
cause I say yes he is so much more than
the first cause
but he is not less than the first cause
and the big philosophical issue of our
time is the question of what is the
first cause and if we roll over and play
dead to the skeptic or the critic of
historic judeo-christianity and they're
willing to negotiate God's being the
Creator and God's being the first cause
we're in serious trouble
that's one of the reasons incidentally
why even in secular universities that
are hostile toward historic Christianity
Today
academic
Integrity demands
the Thomas Aquinas be studied
nobody can study the history of
philosophy without taking this man very
very seriously and the chief reason for
that is because of his formidable
arguing for the existence of God and his
arguments created the classical
synthesis and dominated the intellectual
scene for hundreds and hundreds of years
so that even secular scientists and
philosophers hardly dared to question
the existence of God because to do so
would be to make themselves look as if
they weren't very intelligent because
Saint Thomas had done such a job on them
previously
now to understand how that fell apart we
have to wait until we get to the
critical philosophy of Emmanuel Kant
but again one of the important things
that Aquinas developed in his Arguments
for God from motion from matter and all
of these other things was this concept
that we've already encountered briefly
in San and Saint Anselm the idea of
necessary being
I'm going to translate this into modern
terms and do it as quickly as down and
dirty as I possibly can to make it as
simple as I possibly can
the simple argument is this if anything
exists
something somehow
must have the power of being within it
because if nothing has
self-existent being
nothing could possibly be
if put it another way if there ever was
a time
when there was nothing
what could there possibly be now
except nothing
and so if there is something
there must be something that has the
power of being
or nothing would be
and that which has the power of being
ultimately can't be dependent or derived
contingent being
because if my being is caused by
something other than myself or outside
of myself and then it is caused by
something other than itself and not
other another another
and you go on to What's called the
infinite regress
that's manifest absurdity now not
everybody thought it was
manifestibularity in our day Bert and
Russell had a public debate with
Frederick coppleston the great Roman
Catholic philosopher and coppleston
tried to show Russell that the concept
of an infinite regress is
irrational
and inconceivable and Russell kept
insisting that he could conceive of it
and of course the problem with the
infinite regress is that it takes the
problem of self-exist self-creation
which we've already looked at
and compounds the error infinitely you
don't just have a little bit of nonsense
you have infinite nonsense but in any
case Saint Thomas Aquinas was getting at
the idea that for if anything exists
something must have necessary being now
again there's a little bit of trickiness
here
because the word necessary is used two
different ways
necessary being can mean logical
necessity
meaning that if we are rational if we
are logical logic
necessitates that we postulate the idea
of a self-existent Eternal being
to deny that is to end in
illogical absurdity
so one could say that the idea of God is
a logically necessary idea that's the
kind of thing Anselm was trying to do
but perhaps even more importantly is the
idea that Thomas is talking about when
he talks about necessary being
that God's being is ontologically
necessary
that is we're talking about being
that cannot not be
if self if God is eternal
and he has the power of being within
himself
it means that he exists not by some kind
of external logical necessity
but by the necessity of his own being
because that's what being is that pure
being which has no potentiality
According to Aristotle in this pure form
pure actuality
does not have the power to stop being
because it's eternally
self-existent and self-sufficient
that's why we proliferate attributes
about God in terms of his immutability
his eternality his infinity and all the
rest so it's that kind of thing that
Saint Thomas
talked about the other thing that's
important for Thomas
is the importance he put on What's
called the analogia
antis or the analogy of being
we are human beings God is the Supreme
Being
the difference between the Supreme Being
and the human being is being
I don't have the power of being in and
of myself
there's no logical necessity for anybody
to believe that I exist or that I would
exist a hundred years ago I mean my
birth was not a necessary concept
people could conceive of my never being
born
all right now on the other hand
I don't have necessary being
if I'm a creature
only the Supreme Being has that human
beings are dependent derived contingent
depending on something that does have
eternal being but even though I am not
the Supreme Being and I'm a human being
there is some analogy of being that
exists between God and us
the Bible talks about our being created
in the image of God there is some point
of similarity and this becomes as we
will see later on absolutely vital to
the whole question of whether any
meaningful statement can be made about
God by creatures such as we are
because if there is no point of
similarity between God and us we would
have no grounds for any meaningful
discussion about him and Thomas will
become more and more important with
respect to that issue later on